Inventory of the Henry Cutler Wolfe papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Henry Cutler Wolfe papers
1905-1942
77073
Wolfe, Henry C. (Cutler)
21 manuscript boxes (8.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Contains fictional and journalistic writings, correspondence, printed matter, identification card, medals, and photographs, relating to conditions in the Samara Province of Russia and operations of the American Relief Administration in Russia, and to European politics in the interwar period.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1977.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
An American writer and journalist, Wolfe served as an American Relief Administration worker in Russia during 1922.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection includes correspondence describing Wolfe's experiences abroad during World War I, as well as later trips taken to collect information for lectures. Wolfe was a travelling lecturer and journalist, speaking to audiences at colleges, universities, and organizations throughout the U.S., although mainly in the northeast. The collected clippings and printed materials relate to international relations with a focus on Europe. The collection also contains drafts of Wolfe's various novels, articles, and short stories.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into 4 series: Personal file, Story and article drafts, Printed matter, and Correspondence.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
American Relief Administration.; International relief.; Samara (Russia); Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921--Civilian relief.; United States--Foreign relations.; Europe--Politics and government--1918-1945.; American literature.; Journalists.
Collection Contents
- Personal file, 1812-1937 (Box 1-2)
  - Financial and legal materials, 1812-1937
    - Family receipts, 1812-1915 (Folder 1: 1-2)
    - Deeds, mortgage, insurance, checks, and bank notes, 1882-1930 (Folder 1: 3-4)
    - Stocks, 1937 (Folder 1: 5)
  - Russian visa and Greek rail passes, 1922-1923 (Folder 1: 6)
  - Photographs, undated (Folder 1: 7)
  - Childhood schoolwork, undated (Folder 2: 1)
  - Jane D. Wolfe, Associated Charities minutes and letters, 1932-1936 (Folder 2: 2)
- Story and article drafts, 1926-1940 (Box 2-3)
  - Assorted draft fragments, undated (Folder 2: 3)
  - "Adventures with Vodka", undated (Folder 2: 4)
  - "Allah Be Praised!", undated (Folder 2: 5)
  - "A Belated Christmas Dinner", undated (Folder 2: 6)
  - "Baron Ugurioff's Revenge", undated (Folder 2: 7)
  - "Communism", 1926 (Folder 2: 8)
  - "Danzig Minorities Dispute Threatens German-Polish Relations", undated (Folder 2: 9)
  - "Death Tells a Tale", undated (Folder 2: 10)
  - "European Impressions", 1937 (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Fate Trumps an Ace", undated (Folder 2: 12)
  - "Get Your Man!", undated (Folder 2: 13)
  - "The Golden Minaret", undated (Folder 2: 14)
  - "The Kingdom of the Dawn", undated (Folder 2: 15-16)
  - "Lady Borgia Pours", undated (Folder 2: 17)
  - "Mon Homme", undated (Folder 2: 18)
  - "The Nuns of Starya Maina", undated (Folder 2: 19)
  - "A Pioneer Girl Outwits Chief Red Hawk", undated (Folder 3: 1)
  - "Revenge Solves a Mystery", undated (Folder 3: 2)
  - "Two Hundred Frontiers", undated (Folder 3: 3)
  - "A Weird Experience", undated (Folder 3: 4)
  - "When the Potato Came to France", 1940 (Folder 3: 5)
  - "Whom a Gypsy Loves", 1931 (Folder 3: 6)
  - Untitled draft, undated (Folder 3: 7)
- Printed mattter, 1917-1971 (Box 3-5)
  - "The European Scene," The Columbus Dispatch, 1934-1935 (Folder 3: 8-9)
  - "The European Scene," The Columbus Dispatch, 1934-1935 (Folder 4: 1)
  - The Columbus Dispatch and Coshocton News (Contd.), 1934-1937 (Folder 4: 2-5)
  - The Columbus Dispatch and Coshocton Tribune, 1935-1942 (Folder 5: 1-4)
  - Newspaper clippings, fliers, magazines, and bulletins, 1917-1971 (Folder 5: 5-6)
  - Brochures, 1937 (Folder 5: 7)
  - Foundations of German, undated (Folder 5: 8)
- Correspondence, 1905-1942 (Box 6-21:)
  - Undated (Folder 6: 1-2)
  - February 1905-April 1908 (Folder 6: 3)
  - August 1909-December 1911 (Folder 6: 4)
  - 1912 (Folder 6: 5)
  - 1913 (Folder 6: 6-7)
  - 1915 (Folder 6: 8)
  - 1916 (Folder 6: 9-13)
  - 1917 (Folder 7: 1-7)
  - 1918 (Folder 8: 1-17)
  - 1919 (Folder 9: 1-18)
  - 1920 (Folder 10: 1-14)
  - 1921 (Folder 11: 1-18)
  - 1922 (Folder 12: 1-12)
  - 1923 January-February (Folder 12: 13-16)
  - 1923 March-December (Folder 13: 1-11)
  - 1924 January-April (Folder 13: 12-17)
  - 1924 May-December (Folder 14: 1-17)
  - 1925 (Folder 15: 1-17)
  - 1926 (Folder 16: 1-17)
  - 1927 (Folder 17: 1-5)
  - 1928 (Folder 18: 1-19)
  - 1929 (Folder 18: 20-22)
  - 1930 March (Folder 19: 1)
  - 1931 (Folder 19: 2-3)
  - 1932 March-November (Folder 19: 4-9)
  - 1933 (Folder 19: 10-11)
  - 1934 (Folder 19: 12-14)
  - 1935 (Folder 19: 15-20)
  - 1936 (Folder 19: 21-32)
  - 1937 (Folder 20: 1-14)
  - 1938 January-June (Folder 20: 15-23)
  - 1938 June-November (Folder 21: 1-3)
  - 1939 (Folder 21: 4-13)
  - 1940 (Folder 21: 14-18)
  - 1941 (Folder 21: 19-25)
  - 1942 (Folder 21: 26-31)